בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is ע"ח, Ayin Chet, 78.
We pick up on ע"ז עמוד ב' Ayin Zayin Amud Bet at
the last, like the three lines before the lines get wide at
the two dots, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר מלמדין אותו שלא יחזור.
Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel omer melamdin oto shelo yachzor. So here the
issue was... I'm sorry, we're a little bit before that. אמר מר,
Amar Mar, about ten lines before the lines get wide, you also
have the two dots. So here the issue was that in the
as explaining the משנה Mishna that כל החוזר בו ידו על התחתונה,
kol hachozer bo yado al hatachtona, whoever retracts has the lower hand,
we rather than having it to deal with workers, the ברייתא Baraita
elaborates that it's talking about a sale. That somebody made a down
payment on a piece of land for a thousand שקל shekel or
a thousand סלע, sela, gave two hundred, and then one of the
sides wants to retract. So the consequence is that you give the
two hundred back because it's not considered—we'll get in a minute to
the idea that actually it would be a down payment that you
would
actually jeopardize, that you would actually
lose—but here no, the sale wasn't final, you get the two hundred
back, and the question is you have the lower hand if you're
the side that backed out. So what does that mean? It means
that you get to choose, the other side who didn't back out
gets to choose whether to give you cash or to give you
back land, and they get to choose which land. So if the
seller backs out, the buyer gets to choose, do I want my
cash back, two hundred dollars back, or do I want two hundred
dollars of the best part of the land? And if the seller
backs out—and if the buyer backs out, he gets to choose do
I give him the money or do I give him land, and
if I'm going to give him land, I can give him the
worst part of the land. Okay, so that's the point that whoever
backs out has the lower hand. And some of this might not
be, might more be like חז"ל Chazal establishing these rules, right, rather
than it being some sort of logic inherent mechanism of the system.
You know, because why should that be that you get to decide
which land the person gets and so on? So it might be
that חז"ל Chazal essentially, you know, established these types of penalties. So
let's take a look. About ten lines before the lines get wide,
yep.
I have a clarifying question: so I'm going to buy your field
for a thousand dollars, I give you two hundred. Right. And I
back out. Right. Can I take a small portion that's only
worth two hundred?
Yeah, that's the point. Except, except that's not your choice. If you
back out, that's my choice. Right. Okay. So, אמר מר מהיכן מגביה,
Amar Mar m'heichan magbiya, where do you collect it from? מן העידית.
Min ha-idit. So if the buyer—if the seller backed out, the buyer
gets to choose whether he wants the cash or part of the
land, and he can choose the best part of the land. Okay.
Now, now I've been saying it's the best or the worst part
of the plot that was up for sale, but the גמרא Gemara
initially thinks it doesn't mean that.
קסלקא דעתך מעידית דנכסיו, Kasalka da'atach me-idit de-nechasav, that we mean the
best of any of the lands that the seller has. So the
seller owes me two hundred dollars, he backed out, I can choose
to get not cash but land, and I can pick it from
any of the lands that the guy's got. Now, only two hundred
dollars worth, but still, you'd rather get A-plus property than, you know,
C-minus property. So the גמרא Gemara says why does that make sense?
ולא יהא אלא בעל חוב, V'lo yehei ela ba'al chov, he shouldn't
be stronger than a creditor. So fine, the seller owes me two
hundred dollars.
So דתנן בעל חוב דינו בבינונית, De-tnan ba'al chov dino be-beinonit, even
a creditor is only—where רש"י Rashi says there's like reasons we want
to strengthen the position of a creditor, we want to encourage people
to lend money—and even he only gets to choose, if he has
a lien on the property, middle-grade land, grade B land. So why
here do I get to choose of all the guy's properties the
absolute best, even if I have some lien and some right for
my two hundred dollars back? So the גמרא Gemara says ועוד הא
ארעא דיהיב זוזי, Ve-od ha ar'a de-yahiv zozei, if when the guy
gives back, you know, the seller gives back two hundred dollars worth
of land, he's giving me, you know, it's like cash, you know,
and he has a right to actually—and by the way, if it
really was like a creditor, he could, the person who owes the
money can choose to give back cash, you don't have to give
back land, right? So why should the land
that the seller is giving be worse than cash? Why should this
guy be entitled to the best of all of the property of
the seller? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, right, because—so no, מעידית
שבה ומזיבורית שבה. me-idit sheba u-miziborit sheba. We don't mean when we
talk about the best, the best of all my property, and in
the reverse case where he is the one that backs out, we
don't mean that I can give him the worst of all my
property. I've got some swamp over in Florida, you know. No, it
means from within the plot that was being sold, right, he can
select the best part if I'm the one that backed out, and
I can select the worst part if he's the one that backed
out. Okay, so it's within the plot that to some degree what
we conceptually it seems like what we're saying
is... partial purchase, partial purchase, but because he backed out, you get
to decide which part of that land he bought. Okay, yes.
Is the amount of land somehow
value-based, so if it's the good land and it's a $200 amount,
he gets less of it?
Absolutely, you get less of it. Right, you get maybe an acre
of the best land and 10 acres of the worst land. So
you're only getting your money's worth, okay, but people would still rather
have, you know, the better land than the worst even, you know,
that's the assumption. Okay.
Does land mean for farming?
Yeah, yeah, the assumption here is farming. Right. I mean, you could
also imagine land, you know, you know, in Midtown Manhattan as opposed
to land, you know, somewhere in the middle of nowhere. So you
could say, well, it's more, but nevertheless, you know, highly valued land
is probably a better investment. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: מעידית שבו מזבורית Mi-idit she-bo mi-zib-sh- no, no, we're talking
within the plot of land. רב אחא בריה דרב איקא אמר Rav
Acha brei de-Rav Ika amar אפילו תימא מעידית דנכסיו סתם. Afilu teima
mi-idit de-nechasav stam. No, as- מעידית דנכסיו. mi-idit de-nechasav. No, maybe that
if the buyer backs- if the seller backs out, the buyer can
take the best of the property of the seller, not even limited
to that plot of land, up to his $200. סתם מאן דזבין
ארעא באלפא זוזי, Stam man de-zavin arva be-alfa zuzei,
here's why, because a normal person who sells land for who- you
know, who's excuse me, looking to buy land for a thousand זוז,
zuz, that's an enormous amount of money, okay, אזולי מזיל ומזבין נכסיה.
azulei mazil u-mazbin nichsei. So if I have to put together the
money to raise a thousand זוז zuz to buy this plot of
land, I probably have been selling off my other property at a
discount, right? Because I gotta get together this cash. So I've been
losing money on that sale to get together this cash. So I
gave you $200, I've been doing all this stuff, selling myself at
a discount, I'm getting all this money together, and before I've got
the balance, you back out. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says if
that's true, that actually caused me a loss. Right, that's נזק, nezek,
שווייה כי ניזק. shavya ki-nizak. And I'm like a damaged party. ותנן
U-tenan נזיקין שמין להם בעידית. Nizikin shamin la-hem be-idit. Okay, for נזק,
nezek, you know, for נזק nezek you get the best. And of
course the irony is it doesn't really work that way. Number one,
it's only גרמא, grama, okay, although this gets back to the questions
about גרמי garmi and indirect causation and all those things. Okay, but
number two is, you could still choose if you owe me the
money, I don't have a right to just get the land, I
mean, you get to choose whether to give me cash. If you
don't have cash, right, then, you know, we can talk about which
land I can collect and so on. Anyway, so, but nevertheless, that's
his interpretation. Certainly the פשט, pshat, it's just interesting because a lot
of this case, especially with workers, employers, employees, there's questions about indirect
loss, and it's important to see that we don't always put it
in the גרמא grama category, you know, at least, you know, even
if technically it belongs there, we're willing to sort of redefine things
because of the realities of these situations. But nevertheless, the פשט pshat
here is that it's from within the plot of land that's being
sold. Yes, Charlie?
When was רב אחא בריה דרב איקא? Rav Acha brei de-Rav Ika?
I have no idea. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer מלמדין אותו שלא יחזור בו. Melamdin oso shelo yachzor bo.
Okay, you teach them, okay, this is all true if one of
the sides back out, but that's because a standard partial payment is
considered to not yet be a קנין kinyan on the land. But
he says better let's get people to finalize the deal, okay, both
sides. And let's teach them how to do it even if the
guy only has partial payment. כיצד, Keitzad, how is this possible? כותב
לו אני פלוני בן פלוני Kosev lo ani Ploni ben Ploni etc.
What you do is you say, okay, even if somebody only has
partial payment, take the partial payment, and then write a שטר shtar
that says you're selling- the whole field is sold, and that he
owes you the balance. So that eventually becomes- essentially becomes like a
type of a mortgage, meaning treat it as if it's all been
paid and he owes you the balance. And that's that will finalize
the sale even before the rest of the money is raised. Of
course, peop- you know, there's reasons why one or the other side
might not want to finalize it yet, okay, but he said rather
have it finalized and then we won't have these issues. Okay, טעמא,
ta'ama, so the גמרא Gemara says, דכתב ליה הכי, de-chasav lei hachi,
the reason a partial payment is treated as a full payment plus
a loan is because that's what you explicitly
wrote. הא לא כתב הכי Ha lo chasav hachi לא קני, lo
kani, it wouldn't work, it would only be a partial payment and
as we've seen, you know, either side could still back out. והתניא,
Ve-hatanya, by the way, there's a third possibility that's not being explicitly
explored here, although we'll see it. Right, one is is that it's
doesn't work at all, a partial payment and either side can back
out fully. The other is that it works fully and the rest
is a loan. And the middle possibility is that it's a partial
purchase, right, is that you can back out on the rest, but
you can't back out on, you know, that percentage that you've already
paid for. We haven't yet seen that position. Anyway, let's take a
look. והתניא Ve-hatanya we taught in a ברייתא, baraita, הנותן ערבון לחבירו,
ha-nosein eravon le-chavero, you give a collateral or surety. This really the
fact of the use of the word ערבון eravon makes it much
clearer that we're talking about a type of a down payment and
well, maybe down payment is the wrong word, but
we're not talking about an idea like it's the beginning of the
whole payment, it's more like there's a sense that hold on to
this and there'll be... consequences if we don't go through with the
deal. And what are the consequences? Okay, ואמר לו v'amar lo אם
אני חוזר בי im ani chozer bi if I back out, I
the buyer ערבוני מחול לך ervoni machul lach my collateral here, my
down payment is forgiven to you, meaning that I forfeit my down
payment, okay, which often is how things work with a down payment
on, okay, והלה אומר v'halo omer and then the other one says,
because what's the parallel? The other one says, אם אני חוזר בי
im ani chozer bi if I retract and refuse to sell to
you, אכפול לך ערבונך echpol lach ervonach I will give you back
your down payment plus I'll give you back, I'll give you an
equal amount. That you never heard. Okay, נתקיימו התנאים nitkaymu hat'na'im so
that deal is binding and whatever happens happens, you follow the conditions.
דברי רבי יוסי divrei Rebbi Yose that's what Rebbi Yose says. רבי
יוסי לטעמיה Rebbi Yose l'ta'ameh now the גמרא Gemara interjects. Rebbi Yose
is following his position, דאמר אסמכתא קניא d'amar asmakhta kanya an אסמכתא
asmakhta works. An אסמכתא asmakhta is sort of like a deal based
on possible outcomes, right, where you're sort of assuming it's not going
to happen, right, but and so do we say well you never
really thought you'd back out so you don't have to forfeit it?
No, we say you know what the rules are, it's binding or
whatever, you accept those terms and
you really do have גמר דעת gmar das your full commitment to
actually go through with it. So that's what Rebbi Yose says and
it works. Okay, where are we? אסמכתא קניא asmakhta kanya רבי יהודה
אומר Rebbi Yehuda omer דיו שיקנה כנגד ערבונו dayo sheyikne k'neged ervono
so Rebbi Yehuda says, he seems to be the missing position, and
this is a case of an ערבון eravon it's framed almost as
something that will be forfeited, but nevertheless he says the way it
works is that you own the appropriate proportion of the land based
on the amount of collateral. So it's a partial
purchase. That's what Rebbi Yehuda says. אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל amar
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel במה דברים אמורים bameh d'varim amurim when does
it work that it's treated as a partial purchase? בזמן שאמר לו
bizman she'amar lo ערבוני יקנה ervoni yikne my ערבון eravon will purchase.
Okay now, now רש"י Rashi says, ironically רש"י Rashi says, that means
you tried to say this will purchase the whole thing, but since
it doesn't purchase the whole thing at least you get a partial
purchase. Anyway let's see what he contrasts it to. אבל מכר לו
שדה באלף זוז aval machar lo sadeh b'elef zuz the field was
going for a thousand. ונתן לו מהם חמש מאות זוז v'natan lo
mehem chamesh me'ot zuz and gave him five hundred. Okay, and he
didn't say this was an ערבון eravon and he didn't say ערבוני
יקנה. ervoni yikne. He just said I owe you a thousand, here's
five hundred, I'm getting the rest together, I'll get it to you
in a little while. Okay, so what's the הלכה? halacha? So קנה
ומחזיר לו את השאר אפילו לאחר כמה שנים kana u'machzir lo et
hashear afilu l'achar kamah shanim so that five hundred is considered to
be a purchase of the whole field and the balance he owes
and he has to pay up the balance even if it takes
a couple of years, that works. So that seems to be that
without writing anything special in a שטר shtar just giving partial payment
is treated as full payment plus a loan for the balance. Okay
now, one minute, now and therefore the גמרא Gemara says how does
that fit with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel earlier
who said that you have to explicitly stipulate that and write that
in the שטר shtar in other words it's not קונה koneh at
all. Here we see without stipulating anything it's קונה koneh the whole
thing. Now by the way an interesting conceptual question here is, right,
the way I've been framing it is, is that it's like I
paid it full and then I got back the remainder part as
a loan. But that's conceptually what makes me own the whole plot
of land is that I paid the full amount. There's another way
of conceptualizing it. Conceptualizing it is, you know when an אשה isha
is נקנית בכסף niknet b'chessef this like discussion in the אחרונים acharonim
okay, it doesn't mean that you actually pay her for her market
value, although it might have originally meant that. But it means that
you give something of value and that is symbolic and that finalizes
the deal. Okay so some say well maybe the same is true
here by קרקע karka maybe you don't have to give the full
amount to purchase it. Maybe any amount finalizes the sale, right, it's
like a handshake, it's like חזקה. chazakah. So if I bought a
thousand dollar plot of land from you and I gave you a
dollar, it's not like I gave you a thousand and you lent
me nine hundred ninety-nine. I gave you a dollar, that was the
formal act that finalized the sale and I still owe you the
balance, because that's sort of what we agreed to. So it's a
little different than I gave you the full amount and got it
back. Okay but either way רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel is saying is even in the absence of saying any of
that explicitly, once you start paying it's a purchase on the whole
thing. Yes.
Can you have a ריבית ribit problem if you give part of
the money and five years later you give back the rest of
the money? What's ריבית? ribit? You mean meanwhile you've been gaining the
benefit from the land.
Didn't we have a whole chapter that discussed that question?
It's the opposite. Here the guy who took out the loan had
benefit. I understand, the benefit goes both
ways. No no no no no. ריבית ribit is only if the
lender gets profit, okay. Both borrower and the lender transgress, but ריבית
ribit is only if the person who lent the money is
No, only when it is a case of the lender getting profit
is it considered ריבית Ribbis and then both sides transgress. Okay? But
if the borrower gets extra money for taking out a loan,
that's not fundamentally ריבית-ish. ribbis ריבית Ribbis is that you're paying the
lender for extending the loan. Okay, so now what if the
consideration is about that the lender is taking a loss, like he's
waiting five years to get these funds that he could use?
Right, so that gets back to the other question, which is that
like, if you pay me now, the price is this, if you
pay me later, the price is that. So that would be that
the well there's no lender, the seller, the seller has to be
smart and has to be clear about the stipulation. If the guy
doesn't show up with all the cash in hand, right, he has
to be very explicit what the stipulation is. And the question therefore
becomes exactly that, which is like, what do you do when it's
not stipulated? Okay, so here's the question. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel in one place says if it's not stipulated, it
doesn't purchase at all and you have to stipulate, and in this
place he seems to say that even without stipulating, you purchase the
whole thing. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דקא עייל ונפיק אזוזי
הא דלא קא עייל ונפיק אזוזי. ha d'ka ayil venafik azuzei ha
d'lo ka ayil venafik azuzei. Now this is fascinating because I can
imagine that this would be a nightmare to deal with in a
real court system. It basically says like this: Do we assume
that
this is that I want this, I the seller want it to
be final right now or not, even though you only paid partial?
So the גמרא Gemara says, well, let's look at what else was
going on in my life. If I am running around trying to
raise money, okay, and I'm selling you a plot of land for
a thousand dollars, that's עייל ונפיק אזוזי. ayil venafik azuzei. I'm running
around trying to raise money, right, then we assume that I do
not want this sale to be final unless you actually get me
the full amount of cash. So when you gave me two hundred,
I wasn't, oh okay, fine, you'll pay me the rest later. No,
I'm selling this plot of land because I need cash! If you
can't come up with that cash, it's no sale. Okay? But if
I'm not clearly running around and trying to raise money, then we
assume a partial payment finalizes the sale and you owe the rest.
How was that handled? Why?
I need the money, I'll take whatever I can get right, oh
maybe, but it's an interesting question. And the question also is, is
the running around even after, so I framed it a little bit
differently than רש״י Rashi did and maybe רש״י Rashi will work better
for Charlie's question. Like the way I framed it, the question is
also were you running around for money even after the sale or
only before, even after the guy gave you the partial or before.
Anyway, רש״י Rashi says עייל ונפיק אזוזי, ayil venafik azuzei, and I'm
not sure that רש״י'ס Rashi's read works as much in the sense
of like the running around type of language, but רש״י Rashi says
it means that I am
constantly giving a hard time to the buyer. Do you have the
money yet? Do you have the money yet? Come on, I need
the money! Right? So if I keep on giving a hard time
to the buyer, right, then that shows that I clearly need the
money now and don't want it to be final. Okay, but either
way, one has to imagine that this is an impossible type of
a thing to try to prove in a court of law. How
can, I mean, I guess you could, you could bring witnesses. Look,
he was asking, he was running, whatever, but how do you assess
how much running around for money shows how urgent it was? Also,
if I'm smart and I'm the seller, and if it goes like
רש״י, Rashi, that it's a question, either way if I'm smart and
I'm the seller, I'll say, oh,
I want to get out of the deal. I know what I'll
do! I'll start now after the guy gave me the two hundred
dollars to start nudging him a lot and then that'll entitle me
to get out of the deal without any consequence because that'll, right?
So it's very strange that we look at these sort of circumstantial
things. But anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So whether you
intended to finalize the deal with partial payment, we look at the
evidence of how urgently you needed the money. Yes.
If you do the finalize it with the partial payment, how does
the seller ever get his money back?
It's like a loan. I mean, and he does have a lien
on that plot of land. So he can actually, there is a
mortgage on that plot of land, so he can just take the
land back. Okay, but the problem then being that's sort of what
the גמרא Gemara said before, but then that he wouldn't necessarily get
all of the land back, the price values might have changed from
the time of the sale till now. Okay, the guy might, but
yeah, I mean, he, it's like any normal loan, but that piece
of land definitely serves as collateral.
So it's like a loan even if you're doing the symbolic,
yeah, yeah, I mean that's true, you have to frame it that
way, that's true in order to speak about issues like the lien
and so on, that is correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. הא דעייל והא
דלא עייל ונפיק אזוזי. ha d'ayil veha d'lo ayil venafik azuzei. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, רבא Rava says, האי מאן דזבין מידי לחבריה וקא
עייל ונפיק אזוזי, hai man dezavin midi l'chavrei veka ayil venafik azuzei,
somebody that sells something to his
friend and the seller is going running around for money or רש״י
Rashi says like pressuring him for the
balance, okay, לא קני, lo kani, so he doesn't purchase it.
לא קא עייל ונפיק אזוזי קני, lo ka ayil venafik azuzei kani,
if he's not running around, then it is a good sale. Now
presumably here we mean that It's not clear, we'll clarify in a
minute, presumably here we mean something like this where there's a partial
payment of money and it's a purchase of land, so the כסף
kesef would be קונה. koneh. Does partial payment work? Let's look at
the context. Okay, then let's look at the next case which gets
us beyond land and makes it a little more interesting or complicated.
התם אמר רבא, Hatam amar Rava, Rava says, האי מאן דאוזפי מאה
זוזי לחבריה, hai man de'ozfei mea zuzei le-havrei, somebody lent a hundred
zuz to his friend, I'm sorry, a hundred, a hundred zuz to
his friend. I give you a hundred dollars and Charlie here lent
me the hundred dollars. ופרע זוזא זוזא, u-fara zuza zuza, and every
time Charlie comes to the דף יומי Daf Yomi שיעור, shiur, I
pay him back one dollar of the hundred dollars. Okay, so eventually
he gets his money back, but as we all know, if you
have a single in your pocket, that single somehow disappears. Cup of
coffee, a candy, whatever. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, רבא Rava
says, פירעון הוא, pira'on hu, I did pay him up, אלא דהוי
תרעומת גביה. ela de-havei taroumet gabei. Charlie here has a legitimate complaint
against me. What's his complaint? We're back to the תרעומת. taroumet. What's
the complaint? דאמר ליה אפסדתנהו מינאי, de-amar lei afsadtinhu minai, you made
me, you wasted the money, you know, you made me lose the
money by giving it back to me a dollar at a time.
I didn't do, I wasn't, you know, I, you know, that money
just slipped through my hands and it disappeared. Okay, now back to
our case about partial payment. ההוא גברא דזבין ליה חמרא לחבריה. hahu
gavra de-zavin lei hamra le-havrei. Somebody sold חמרא hamra to his friend.
Now חמרא, hamra, you know, it can mean wine or a donkey.
I normally assume when we're talking about sales it means wine. For
some reason רש״י Rashi thank you, thank you, fast for some reason
רש״י Rashi makes a point of saying here חמור. hamor. So there's
an interesting question, like why did רש״י Rashi here have to clarify
that it's a donkey rather than wine? Not clear. Anyway, we'll go
with רש״י. Rashi. Somebody sold a donkey to his friend, ופש ליה
חד זוזא. u-pish lei had zuza. Okay, so I sold Charlie here
my donkey, Charlie paid me ninety-nine dollars, the price was a hundred.
Okay, so is it a final sale or not? So this is
the question, not full amount.
וכאיי ונפיק אזוזי, ve-ka'ayei ve-nafik azuzei, and I've been running around trying
to collect funds. Okay, so the question is, is paying ninety-nine out
of the hundred dollars, shouldn't that finalize the sale? How could we
say for even one dollar remaining it's not final even if I
do need the money urgently? So יתיב רב אשי וקא מעיין בה,
yativ Rav Ashi ve-ka me'ayein bah, Rav Ashi was sitting and he
was looking into this. כי האי גוונא מאי, ki hai gavna mai,
what's the story with this? קני או לא קני, kanei o lo
kanei, does it work or not? אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב אשי,
amar lei Rav Mordechai le-Rav Ashi, Rav Mordechai said to Rav Ashi,
הכי אמר אבימי מהגרוניא משמיה דרבא, hachi amar Avimi me-Hagronya mi-shmei de-Rava,
here's what Avimi said in the name of Rava, זוזא כזוזי דמי,
zuza ke-zuzei dami, one dollar is like a lot of dollars, ולא
קני, ve-lo kanei, and it doesn't work. Obviously you sort of understand
this because like, you know, okay, one, you know, one dollar does
work, how about two? How about three? Like you got to like,
you got to draw a line, so you got to say any
less than full payment, here's the rule. Okay, but the problem is
that we're being contextual about everything about the whole major issue. If
he's running around to raise the money then it's not final, if
he's not running around it is final. That we can be contextual
about. But owing one dollar versus owing eight hundred dollars, they would
say no, no, no, we have to be black and white, any
money owed is not final. Okay, so that's interesting. But the other
important point is we're talking here not about land, we're talking here
about chattel. And chattel, you do not need the money to make
the sale final. So what is the relevance here of discussing the
money? So תוספות Tosafot says, it's תוספות Tosafot says but rejects, he
says you could say we're talking about a מי שפרע. mi she-para.
If you paid partially and not fully, you know, and then you
back out, do you get the מי שפרע? mi she-para? Remember the
מי שפרע mi she-para when you pay and you haven't done, or
is that only after it's fully been paid? But תוספות Tosafot doesn't
like that, תוספות Tosafot says what this seems to indicate is, and
this is very interesting, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, נראה דאיירי
אפילו משך המקח. nira de-ayri afilu mashach ha-mekach. Okay, even if I
pull the purchase, if I didn't specify at the time of sale,
משיכה זו תהא קונה חפץ זה. meshicha zu tehei konah chefetz zeh.
So if I know that Charlie is going crazy to raise funds
and he sells me like, you know, and he sells me I
don't know, his car, and I drive it off, okay, because it's
in a context where he urgently needs the money and you haven't,
and I haven't paid him, even, I only paid him ninety percent
or ninety-nine percent, okay, so normally I wouldn't have to pay him
a penny for it to be final, I would just have to
take possession, right, and then I'd owe him the money. But in
a case where he urgently needs the money we assume that his
דעת da'at is not to finalize the sale until he gets payment
in full. So again, oh my god, that just like changes everything,
you know, it radicalizes, you know, like it just, you know, disrupts
everything we've been learning. Every sale that we've assumed is final when,
you know, for chattel when the person takes possession, now we're finding
out is not final until payment in full in a case where
it's clear that the guy urgently needed to raise the funds. Okay,
so now you're going to have, imagine how much that's going to
clog up the court system debating all those cases. All right, yeah.
There's something I, I don't know if I'm appreciating exact, I mean
I get what you're saying, but I would have thought like, if
I drive off with your car it's really close to an act
of גניבה. geneivah.
What are you talking about? We sold it, you agreed to sell
it, you did a קנין. kinyan. What an act of גניבה? geneivah?
I come into your store, I take... So if you're agreed to
sell to me, I take possession of the eggs. Sure, if I
walk off with the eggs, it's גניבה. geneiva. If I'm saying to
you, will you sell me the eggs? Yes. How much? Two dollars.
Great. And you take it and you pay later, right? It has
to be clear you're not running away with it. You've agreed to
pay later. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Where were we? Okay. So that's big, that this idea of
needing the money and it's not finalized until then is not just
a question of קנין כסף kinyan kesef for land, but also
holds in abeyance the question of even a transaction of cattle, according
to one way of reading this גמרא. Gemara. Okay. אמר ליה רב
אחא בריה דרב יוסף לרב אשי. Amar lei Rav Achai brei de-Rav
Yosef le-Rav Ashi. So Rav Achai said to Rav Ashi, והא אמרינן
משמיה דרבא קני, ve-ha amrinan mishmei de-Rava kani, how can you say
that owing a dollar is not finalized? We say in the name
of רבא Rava that if you paid it all up except the
dollar it is final. Okay. So אמר ליה תסקרגם שמעתיך במוכר שדה
מפני רעתה. amar lei tiskargem shemateich bemocheir sadeh mipnei ra'asah. So now
we're getting a counterbalancing factor. I mean oh my god, like, you
know, this is, I mean, sometimes we complain, I complain, whatever, whatever,
that הלכה halacha is too formalistic, especially in like a דיני ממונות
dinei mamonos realm, right? גרמא Gerama is פטור, patur, you know, I
mean come on, there cases whatever. But the problem is if you're
too contextual and you don't have clear ways of measuring it like
it's gonna be impossible to assess. Sometimes you need rules, right? But
here all of a sudden it's like it's all context. So on
the one hand, if I'm running around trying to raise the money,
it's not sale, it's not a full sale until you pay me
in full. On the other hand, even if I'm running around trying
to raise the money, if it's clear that this property that I'm
selling you is like a bad piece of property and I'm happy
to get it off my hands, then that counterbalances the evidence of
me running around for the money and then we say it's a
final sale even if you haven't paid me in full. Okay so
now every case, right? There was a partial payment. Was it a
sale or not? So one side's gonna try to prove he was
running away from, you know, to continue running around trying to collect
the money. The other side is gonna try to prove that no
he was just trying to offload this piece of land and so
on, right? So there's like a lot of external things that have
to be debated and proved. Okay but that's what we're saying. If
you're trying to offload the piece of property, then even if you
are running around for money, the sale is final, even if it's
only partial payment.
תסקרגם שמעתיך tiskargem shemateich means your teaching is rocky?
No, no. Translated in the following context.
Okay, so פשיטא pshita says the גמרא, Gemara, it's obvious, איבעי לזבוני
במאה. ba'ei lizvonei be-mei'ah.
Now I want to sell a plot of land for a hundred.
This is a case where I'm running around for money, I need
to raise money, so we're gonna say that it's not gonna be
final until it's payment in full. Okay and I need a hundred
dollars. And I have a little plot of land for a hundred
dollars, ולא אשכח velo ashcach and I can't find any buyers for
this little plot of land. וזבין במאתים. vezavin be-ma'asayim. Then I sell
a bigger, nicer piece of property for two hundred. I only needed
to raise a hundred, but I was in a bind, so I
had to sell a bigger piece of property for two hundred. Okay,
וקא עייל ונפיק אזוזי veka'ayil venafik azuzei
and I've clearly I need to raise the money. So and there
was not full payment. So in that case לא קני. lo kani.
Clearly it's not final. I need to raise the money,
okay, and you know and it's not מוכר שדה מפני רעתה, mocheir
sadeh mipnei ra'asah, right?
I actually sold a plot of land I really didn't even want
to sell. So when it's, I'm not trying to offload the property
and I need to raise the funds, if you don't pay me
in full it's not final.
Did he sell a hundred dollars worth?
No, you sold the whole plot. You actually regretted it. You had
to sell a bigger plot of land, you didn't even need that
amount of money, but you had to sell.
It was a partial payment, right?
But he only paid, right, but it
needs to be pay a hundred.
Oh that's an interesting question. That would make that a bigger חידוש,
chiddush, although the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, right? The חידוש chiddush
in like maybe he did pay the hundred, so I raised the
money I needed to raise, oh that would be a really interesting
question. So then would that be enough of וקא עייל ונפיק... veka'ayil
venafik... that's a good question. I don't know. The גמרא Gemara doesn't
ask that though. But that's a very good question. Okay so אלא
ela but here's the גמרא's Gemara question. איבעי לזבוני במאה. ba'ei lizvonei
be-mei'ah. I needed to raise a hundred dollars. ולא אשכח velo ashcach
and I couldn't find any buyers for my hundred for my small
plot of land. ואיתרחווי משכח, ve'itarchavvei mashcach, if I would have hustled
a little bit, I could have found buyers. I'm a lazy, and
you know, I'm a lazy bum. Okay I didn't, I just, you
know, put up one posting on Craigslist, I figured that'll be it,
nobody answered, all right, whatever. So וזבין במאתים vezavin be-ma'asayim and then
I sold my nicer plot for
two hundred. וקא עייל ונפיק אזוזי veka'ayil venafik azuzei and it's clear
I need to raise the funds. So if I just couldn't be
bothered to try to sell the smaller one and I sold the
bigger one, so the question is is that like מוכר שדה מפני
רעתה? mocheir sadeh mipnei ra'asah? Is that enough evidence that I really
don't care about this bigger plot of land, right? It's like I
really just want to get rid of it. Because I really cared
about it, I would have hustled a little more to sell the
smaller plot of land rather than having to sell the bigger one.
So גמרא Gemara says מאי, mai, what's the story there? כמוכר שדה
מפני רעתה דמי או לא? kemocheir sadeh mipnei ra'asah dami o lo?
How do we translate my laziness? Okay, is my laziness showing I
don't really
care about
Anyway, so גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teyku, we don't know. Okay, but
now it becomes again very interesting. On the one hand, not full
payment could sometimes maybe hold back even a purchase of chattel if
somebody clearly needs to raise funds. And in terms of land, where
it's the money that does the deal, okay, does it you need
full payment or not? On the one hand, if the guys need
to raise the funds, you do need full payment. If he doesn't,
you don't need full payment. But even when he does need to
raise the funds, okay, if he's also offloading this property which he
really doesn't wants to offload anyway, then that counterbalances that and then
you wouldn't need full payment. So it becomes a very complicated calculus
and then try to proving all of that. Okay, let's finish up
now from the previous משנה, mishna, from the first משנה. mishna. שכר
את החמור ואת הקדר שוכר עליהם או מטען. sakhar es hachamor ve'es
hakadar socheir aleihem o mat'an. So here's the case about which where
the workers back out and it's a דבר האבד, davar ha'avad, you
know, my stuff is going to go to waste if I don't
really get something. I mean, one good example it's not only a
monetary דבר האבד, davar ha'avad, the band, the wedding band backs out
at the last minute, you know, my daughter's wedding is tonight, you
know, what I'm supposed to do? Now there's no music? Okay, so
there's some financial loss or there's some serious loss because you guys
backed out at the last minute. So anyway, so it says I
can go ahead and either trick them and tell them I'll pay
them double and not, or I can hire other people and have
them pay for it. But the question is going to be how
are you going to get them to pay for it, right? So
let's take a look.
עד כמה שוכר עליהם? ad kama socheir aleihem? Until how much, how
much more can you spend to hire other people and to get
them to pay the difference? So אמר רב נחמן עד כדי שכרן.
amar Rav Nachman ad k'dei secharan. You could up up to, now
that sounds like it could be double, but רש״י Rashi says what
it means is until the amount that they've earned so far. So
the case of the band wouldn't be a good example. They were
working on my flax, they did half a day, if they don't
finish it, the flax is going to spoil, go to waste.
Okay, but they deserve 100 dollars for the work they've done so
far. I can use the full amount that I owe them because
it's still in my possession to go ahead and to add that
to hire someone else. So the point is like what because part
of what's not spelled out here is essentially it's these are not
the mechanics of other things like נזק nezek and whatever, חז״ל Chazal
essentially are creating a certain type of employment laws or, you know,
consequences and so on. So like if I were to try to
sue them in court to pay for my loss that I had
to hire other people, like on the basis of what? Like גרמא?
grama? Right, whatever happens to גרמא grama being פטור. patur. Do we
have to say it's גרמי, garmi, what is גרמי? garmi? So it
sounds like that חז״ל Chazal adopted a middle position which is, you're
not going to sue them in court, what you're going to do
is if you have their money already in your possession because it's
their fee, then we're going to let you use the money you
owe them to go ahead and hire replacements. Okay, so it's not
the, but it sounds like, right, if I didn't have that on
me, you know, on it, I would not even if they had
money in their bank account, it sounds like I can't sue them
in court. What חז״ל Chazal have let me do is take the
money I owe them and use that to hire other replacements.
And they get nothing. And what?
And they get nothing. You backed out in the middle of the
day, I'm going to I can use up to the full amount
that I owe you to hire your replacement.
You didn't say if those workers get paid
in advance.
No.
We didn't say. No. Okay. But if they have already been
paid, then it's too late. Right. That's what it sounds like. It's
not just it'll be hard for me because I have to sue
them, it sounds like no, they all, you know, I don't have
any I don't have any action in this case.
Of course, it's like what? It's like you would think if you'd
already paid them then they would owe you more because
I had right because you get paid
in advance. Rent?
Right. No, but rent also gets paid at the end. שכירות אינה
משתלמת אלא בסופו. schirus einah mishtalemes ela b'sofo. Every it all gets
paid at the end. Okay. Okay. איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן, eisvei Rava
l'Rav Nachman, Rava challenged Rav Nachman. ארבעים וחמישים זוז. arba'im ve'chamishim zuz.
We had a ברייתא braisa earlier that said even forty or fifty
זוז, zuz, which is, you know, a large sum presumably much more
than you owed them, you know, for for whatever half day's work
they did. אמר ליה כי תניא ההיא שבאה חבילו לידו. amar lei
ki sanya hi sheba chavilo l'yado. No,
that's a case where they have dropped off their packages in in
your possession, meaning that they came by to do the work. Imagine
the case of the band, okay, they brought all of their equipment
to the wedding hall and then they basically you know and then
they basically said that they're going to have to cancel. So I
said, okay, I hijacked all their equipment and I got you know
to hire a replacement band. So that's what you can do. If
you have their possessions in your hand, and רש״י Rashi says it's
like the equipment that they would bring for the work, they dropped
it off at your place, fine, I'll sell all your equipment, no
problem, I'll hire a replacement.
Alright, so now moving on, next משנה. mishna. These are very complicated
because you know you have like רחמנות rachmanus for the workers, but
you also have רחמנות rachmanus for the employer. He's being left high
and dry, right? So you know, but the one thing important to
remember and I should remind us is that it did say, the
גמרא Gemara did say earlier based on one read of the ברייתא,
Braitah, that if it was really unforeseeable circumstances, if the worker had
a death in the family, the גמרא Gemara actually dealt with that,
a death in the family or got sick, right, then even in
a דבר האבוד davar ha-avud they don't suffer a loss. But if
it's not a tragic circumstance or, you know, completely uncontrolled circumstance like
that, then you don't want me to sell off your equipment, you
show up for the, for the, you know, for my daughter's wedding,
end of story. Okay, let's look at the next משנה. Mishnah. השוכר
את החמור להוליכה בהר והוליכה בבקעה. Hasocher es hachamor l'holicho be-har v'holicho
be-bik'ah.
Now, this is like a radical shift. We're going from questions about
workers' laws, which is a type of שכירות—but schirus I employ you
for your service—to a very different type of a thing. I hire
your donkey. Those are a very different set of laws. That's like
the case, you know, it's sort of like שומרים, shomrim, right? You
can take, I have your possession, I can be a, a, a
somebody who guards it for free, a שומר חנם, shomer chinam, or
somebody who guards it for pay, a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, or
I could have your object in my possession because I'm making use
of it. I am borrowing it, I'm a שואל, shoel, or I
am renting it, I'm a שוכר. socher. But that's a very different
type of an arrangement. That's like, that's not a contract for service,
that's like a right to use a particular object. It's almost like
a partial purchase. You know, one way the רמב"ם Rambam conceptualizes it
is that it's a purchase, a limited purchase, a purchase for a
limited time for its use. I own not the title of it,
but I own it for its use for a limited time. You
don't have to conceptualize it like that; it just might be a
right to use it for a limited amount of time. But again,
conceptually, it's a completely different issue than a contract of service. Yeah.
You, you, I'm renting a truck.
Well right, a truck, exactly. So השוכר את החמור להוליכה בהר והוליכה
בבקעה. Hasocher es hachamor l'holicho be-har v'holicho be-bik'ah. Now we get to
a different set of questions. Not what if one of the sides
of a contract backs out, but what if you used it against
the sort of conditions of the rental? Okay, you said 'I need
to use this, I'm going to take it up on the
mountains' and that was understood, you know, and you went ahead and
instead did it by way of the valley. Okay, it's an interesting
question like what means להוליכה בהר? l'holicho be-har? Did the, did the
renter say to you 'I'm only renting this to you with the
understanding that you only use it on the mountains' or is it
even no, it sounds much less formal. It's like that was understood,
that was taken, that was like the assumption that I'm, you know,
'oh where are you', you know, like when they, sometimes you rent
a car—if you want to use that example—they say 'where are you
going to be driving, how far are you going to be driving?'
Right, go ahead, high roads.
No, but that's the question. I don't know that you have to
say 'don't'; there's just some assumption that this is going to be
where you're going to be using it and you used it in
another case. But that's the important question. Was there some explicit statement
'only X, not Y' or was it just like, no, that was
like the presumption that that was going to be the case? Okay,
והוליכה בבקעה, בבקעה והוליכה בהר. v'holicho be-bik'ah, be-bik'ah v'holicho be-har. Or the
reverse. אפילו זו עשר מילין וזו עשר מילין, Af'ilu zo eser milin
v'zo eser milin, even if the distance was the same, there didn't
seem to be any more particular effort or whatever, ומתה, u-meisah, and
it drops dead, חייב. chayav. Now this becomes to be the quest
about, about פשיעה, p'shiah, right? That's going to be how it's going
to be conceptualized. And also a long תוספות Tosafos on the question
of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס. t'chilaso b'p'shiah v'sofo b'ones. Okay, but basically
I was, was I negligent? That's the important question. Was I negligent
in taking it in a different place if there's no particular reason
to be concerned that the different place would be an issue? Or
maybe even if I wasn't negligent, maybe by virtue of the fact
that I violated the terms of the agreement, especially if the terms
were explicit and so on, okay, does that make me therefore liable
for anything that's going to happen afterwards? So it sounds like a
type of a תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס, t'chilaso b'p'shiah v'sofo b'ones, okay,
and I'm חייב. chayav. But now let's read the next line of
the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, השוכר את החמור להוליכה בהר והוליכה בבקעה. Hasocher
es hachamor l'holicho be-har v'holicho be-bik'ah. So now you said it was
going to be on the mountain and it was in the valley.
אם החליקה, Im hichlikah, פטור. patur.
If it slipped, you know, and broke a leg, by slipping, you're
exempt because the assumption is the mountainous terrain is much more slippery.
So when I brought it in the valley, I actually was being
more responsible in terms of the issue about slipping. So obviously I'm
going to be exempt; there was no negligence from the perspective of
slipping. אבל אם הוחמה, Aval im huchmah, but if it got overheated,
it's a lot hotter in the bottom of the valley than the
top of the mountain, so I was negligent about that, חייב, chayav,
I'm חייב. chayav. And the reverse is true if I took it
in the mountain rather than the valley. Okay, להוליכה בבקעה והוליכה בהר,
l'holicho be-bik'ah v'holicho be-har, the agreement was to do it in the
valley and I did it on the mountain. אם החליקה, Im hichlikah,
חייב. chayav. If it slipped, I'm חייב chayav because that's negligence, that
it's more slippery terrain. ואם הוחמה, V'im huchmah, and if it died
of sunstroke or something, פטור, patur, I'm exempt. Okay, now this sounds
like it's not 'once I violate the terms, you're absolutely liable'. It
sounds like only if my negligence was linked to what happened in
the end. If I was negligent, right, if I was negligent about
X and X happened, I'm חייב. chayav. But if I was negligent
about X and Y happened, I'm פטור. patur. So which one is
it? So the גמרא Gemara is going to try to unpack that.
Okay, אם מחמת המעלה חייב. Im machmas hamala chayav.
However, if it's
clear that the reason the donkey died was because of the exertion
of going up the mountain, then I'm also חייב. chayav. Then it's
not a question of
was it slippery or was it hot? There's an extra exertion there
and if it's evident. Now, תוספות Tosafot says, how do you know?
You went up the mountain and it was fine and then ten
minutes later it dropped dead. Was it dropping dead because of the
exertion? Like how do you measure those things?
Well, that's true. That's interesting.
But I imagine that the slope is—yeah, it's a good question. Okay.
Right. Right. Okay. Now, השוכר את החמור והבריקה, Hasoker es hachamor vehivrika,
you rented a donkey. A totally different point here. You rented a
donkey and the גמרא, Gemara, we'll see what the גמרא Gemara says
הוריקה hivrika means, but one reading is like it's got something in
its eye. So it's now basically can't see well, so you can't
use it as much. Okay.
או שנעשה אנגריא O shenasa angarya or it was basically seized by
the government, by the king. Okay. In that case, but again we'll
see that that does not mean that it is totally inaccessible to
you. To some degree, it's somewhat seen as somewhat accessible but not
fully. We'll see what that is in the גמרא. Gemara. אומר לו
הרי שלך לפניך. Omer lo harei shelcha lefanecha. The renter can say
to you, okay,
your donkey is still rented for the rest of the week. You
can't ask for a refund. Go ahead and use it. So it's
a little hard for you to get to. You deal with that.
You took out the full rental for the week. That's not my
problem. Okay. אבל מתה או נשברה, Aval mesa o nishbera, if it
died or if it got broken and presumably not due to my
negligence, the way in which
I'm פטור patur from it being broken. In that case, you can
say it's not usable anymore. חייב להעמיד לו חמור. Chayav le'ahamid lo
chamor. Then I have to replace it. Which is an interesting question.
I rent a car, right? And I don't know what the law
is here. I rent a car and there's an accident. Has nothing
to do with me. Okay, I'm totally not negligent, right? I get
rear-ended, whatever, it's not usable. I assume the car company has a
responsibility. They can't say drive it with a fender scraping on the
ground. They have a responsibility to
get me a new car. But they can't always do
that
by the side of the road.
Right. You don't take out insurance.
All right, that's a different conversation.
That's true. Anyway, so
in this case, right, anyway, you if it's not usable by the
other person, then you have to replace it. If it's still usable
although harder to use, that's not your responsibility. That's the basic rule.
רש״י Rashi frames it in an interesting way. Why are they responsible
to replace it? Why don't they say go ahead and use it,
it's dead, so you rented it for the week, so now you
have the rental of a dead donkey? So רש״י Rashi seems to
sort of get to the fact that there's also something contractual between
us that then you have to live up to those terms of
the contract. It's not just an ownership of that piece of that
donkey. But רש״י Rashi frames it a little bit like I have
a lien on the donkey for the rights of—like somehow makes it
still more of like a little bit of a property right. If
you look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says, חייב. Chayav. רש״י Rashi
says, המשכיר למכור העור והנבלה לכלבים ולהוסיף מעות ולהעמיד לו חמור או
ישכור לו אחר בדמי נבלה. Hamas kir limkor ha'or vehaneveila lechlavim ulehosif
ma'os uleha'amid lo chamor o yiskar lo acher bidmei neveila.
So רש״י Rashi consistently emphasizes, sell the donkey and get my replacement.
שהרי חמור זה שיעבד לו, Sheharei chamor ze shi'ebed lo, because this
donkey
is—I have a lien on it to have usage of a donkey.
So I can force you to sell the dead donkey to satisfy
the terms of the contract. But the point רש״י Rashi says is
that that's not just—it's not limited to that, because you might have
to add a lot of money to buy a replacement donkey to
the dead donkey. But it is interesting the way he frames it
as a type of a property right. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara.
That makes sense also with נשברה nishbera because that's such a funny
word to use about a living thing.
Oh, that's a good point too. Right, I mean there's—is it metaphorical?
נשברה רגלו Nishbera raglo or something like—maybe, yeah.
Okay,
let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי שנא רישא דלא קמפליג ומאי
שנא סיפא דקמפליג. Mai shna reisha d'lo kamaplig u'mai shna seifa d'kamaplig.
Why in the beginning part of the משנה, Mishna, when I took
it in the on the mountain and I should've taken it in
the valley and it drops dead, I'm liable regardless, whereas in the
סיפא, Seifa, it seems only when I can draw a line of
connection between my negligence and what happened. So which one is it?
Do you have to draw that line of connection or not? That's
like the question. That's the question of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס. Tchilaso
b'pshia v'sofo b'ones. Do you have to draw that line of connection
or not? So אמר דבי רבי ינאי, Amar d'vei Rabbi Yannai, רישא
שמתה מחמת אויר. Reisha shemeisa machmas avir.
In the beginning, it was—it died due to the change of air.
And there, there's clearly a different air up on the mountain or
in the valley. And since the air is different and we can
somehow tell—I don't know how you can tell that it died as
a result of the air. I'll discuss that in a minute. But
somehow you saw that it was, you know, but in that case
דאמרינן אוירא דהרא קטלה דאמרינן אוירא דביקעא קטלה. D'amrinan avira d'hara katla
d'amrinan avira d'bikea katla.
There we say, oh, clearly there was some connection. The air quality
was different. It's not a question of hot or cool or whatever.
It's something— Thinking about just the mountain air, you know, the thinner
air, the thicker air, or whatever it is, and therefore we assume
that there yes, it was connected, whereas in the other case there
was another thing that killed it, it was clear, it slipped, it
was clear and it, you know, it was clear it died of
sunstroke. So there we're trying to draw well, sunstroke is more likely
here and less likely there, slipping is the reverse. So there we
say we have to figure out which way it's connected. But the
air, it's not better or worse, it's just different. So if it
died, if you took it in the wrong place, we'll just say
it's the different quality of the air that did it.
It's a way of saying, if you took it to a place
that it was not understood where you should go.
Well, that is the question, is the גמרא Gemara saying that it's,
right,
I'm going to get to that, okay? Whether it's just a way
of saying that without evidence to the contrary, we're going to assume
it's related. That might be what it says. Let's read the next
answer. רבי יוסי בר חנינא אומר כגון שמתה מחמת אוצנא. Rabbi Yose
bar Chanina omer kigone shemeit machmat utzna.
It died as a result of the, of being, of, of weariness.
Now רש"י Rashi says that's obvious what the causation is if you
took it up the mountain, right? Because then it worked harder to
go up the mountain. What about if you took it in the
valley? So רש"י Rashi says,
where were we?
If you look at רש"י Rashi four lines from the bottom, ואם
העלה להוליכה בבקעה אף על פי שלא ראינוהו מזיעת, veim he-ehla lo
leracheh bebika af al pi shelo ra-inu-hu me-za-et,
so you took it in the valley and we didn't see it
sweating, nevertheless, okay, ולא היה חם מאד לומר הוכמה יש לומר, velo
haya cham meod lomar huchma yesh lomar, you still could claim אם
הלכה בהר היה אויר שולט שם, im hohlcha bahar haya avir sholet
sham, no,
if it were going on the mountain, it would have exerted more,
but it would have been the nice mountain air, ונותן בכח, venoten
bakoch, and that would have strengthened it, ולא תיגע תחת משאה בבקעה
דלא שולי בי אוירא, velo tiyaga tachat masa-o bebika delo sholi be
avira, but on the valley, there was the bad air, always getting
back to the air quality, there was the exert. So this sounds
like the, what was he saying, which is, this sounds like we
really can't draw any obvious lines of connection, but what we're going
to say is, right, there are cases where it's clearly unconnected. You
took it in a, you know, you took it in the valley
and it died by slipping. Okay, now slipping was much more likely
in the mountain. Clearly there, there's no connected negligence. Of course, though,
you could always argue, what do you mean? It wouldn't have been
in that exact plot of land where it slipped, you know. But
anyway, but in that case, there's one case, one extreme where the
negligence clearly was not related to what happened, or there was, you
know, no negligence linked to what happened. It slipped and you were
actually being more responsible regarding slipping. That case you're פטור. patur. There's
the other extreme which is you can clearly connect the dots, okay?
You took it on the mountain and it died because of, you
know, because of slippage, okay? So you were negligent about slipping and
it died, that you're clearly חייב. chayav. And the big question, and
this is really the question of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס, tchilaso bepshiya
vesofo beones, which this גמרא Gemara now seems to be saying is
חייב, chayav, is when it's not clearly connected and not clearly unconnected.
Are you חייב chayav or not? Are we going to say that
now because you were negligent, we're going to assume that anything happened
was your fault related to the negligence, unless you could absolutely prove
that they're completely unrelated, right? And that seems to be what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. Even if it drops dead, we don't know
why it died, it's air, who knows what the air is different
on the bottom or the top, right? It was weary, even though
you took it at a place where it required less exertion, right?
All those cases if we don't know, we're going to assume you're
חייב. chayav. All right? And the only case you're פטור patur is
when clearly you were more responsible and not negligent about what, about
the circumstances about why it died. Yeah.
It's like voiding the warranty, right?
Oh,
interesting. So the גמרא Gemara is now, so I've been framing it
as an issue of negligence and תחילתו בפשיעה tchilaso bepshiya and we
assume once negligence began, we'll interpret everything as resulting from the negligence.
The גמרא Gemara now is going to deal with something closer to
the concept of just voiding the warranty. So let's see what, where
the גמרא Gemara is going to go. Okay, רבא אמר כגון שהכישה
נחש. Rava amar kigone shehikisho nachash. That's another perfect example. It was
bit by a snake. Was that related or not related? We have
no idea, but we're just going to assume if you were in
the other place, there wouldn't have been snakes. Okay. All right.
רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan. So anyway, those are answers which is we have no
idea why and you're going to be חייב, chayav, you know, if
we have no idea why it happened. You're only going to be
פטור patur when we can clearly say you were not negligent about
that, you actually more responsible in terms of why that, you know,
from that perspective. Now that's one explanation which is like a תחילתו
בפשיעה וסופו באונס. tchilaso bepshiya vesofo beones. Now we have another one.
רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן הא מני רבי מאיר היא.
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan ha mani Rabbi Meir hi.
No, no, no. The רישא reisha you're right sounds like even if
there's no point of connection, the סיפא seifa sounds like there has
to be a point of connection. What's really going on is that
it's a debate of תנאים. tana-im. The first part of the משנה
mishna that says that you're חייב chayav even if there's no connection
to what you did wrong, that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. What does
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say? דאמר כל המעביר על דעת בעל הבית
נקרא גזלן. deamar kol hamavir al daas baal habayis nikra gazlan. That
if you violate the terms of the owner, A, there's an assumption
that it's wrong and you do something, you've done something wrong by
violating the terms. and there are consequences. The consequence is you're using
the owner's object and you violated the terms. That's now like you're
a גזלן gazlan on the object, and you are now חייב chayev
for anything that happens. Okay, you have full liability after that stage.
So that's the first position in the משנה. Mishnah. It's not that
we say it's resulted from פשיעה. peshiya. It's not about פשיעה. peshiya.
פשיעה peshiya could be even if I didn't violate the terms. We
didn't make any terms. I was just negligent. That's a different conversation.
This is about consequences, penalties for violating the terms. Once I'm violating
the terms, I'm using your object illegitimately in a certain sense and
I'm like a גזלן gazlan and I'm fully liable. Okay, so the
רישא reisha is that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir position. The סיפא seifa
doesn't hold that way. The סיפא seifa feels that you need to
actually be able to connect what I did wrong to what happened.
So let's now get to the גמרא Gemara establish which רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir it is. We're going to make a push to at
least finish to the two dots. האי רבי מאיר, Hai Rebbi Meir,
which רבי מאיר? Rebbi Meir? אילימא רבי מאיר דצבא, Ileima Rebbi Meir
detzava, the רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir of the case of the dyer.
דתנן: Detnan: הנותן צמר לצבא לצבוע לו אדום וצבעו שחור, Hanosan tzemar
letzava litzboa lo adom utzvao shachor, you give wool to be dyed
red and he dyed it black. שחור וצבעו אדום, Shachor utzvao adom,
or the reverse. רבי מאיר אומר, Rebbi Meir omer, נותן לו דמי
צמרו. nosan lo dmei tzemaro. You've purchased the wool effectively by doing
the wrong thing. Pay him for the wool and it ends there.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer, no. אם השבח יתר על היציאה
נותן לו את היציאה. Im hashevach yaser al hayetzia nosan lo es
hayetzia. If the improvement was more than the expenses, then he only
has to pay you for the expenses, not for your normal fee.
אם היציאה יתירה על השבח, Im hayetzia yesira al hashevach, if the
expenses were more than the improvement because you did a really bad
job, נותן לו את השבח, nosan lo es hashevach, he only pays
you for the improvement. Basically, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says the owner
still owns the wool and you renegotiate how much he has to
pay you because you did the wrong thing. But רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir says you own the wool. So basically, here you go, you
changed the terms and now you've taken possession of it. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says ממאי, Mimai, how do you know that that's
applicable here? דילמא שאני התם דקנייה בשינוי מעשה. Dilma shani hasam dekanya
bishinui ma'aseh.
There, when you change the terms, you actually change the object and
that's a type of a קנין kinyan of making a change in
the object. When I took the donkey on the mountain, okay, I
didn't yet change it when it died. It was a different donkey.
When I took it up the mountain, that didn't yet make me
own the donkey. So just because here you own by changing doesn't
mean that in other cases you change and you've now become a
גזלן. gazlan. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא האי
רבי מאיר, Ela hai Rebbi Meir, the following רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir.
דמגבי פורים, Demagbi Purim, the רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir of collecting money
for Purim. דתניא: Detanya: מגבי פורים לפורים, Magbi Purim le-Purim, money collected
for Purim has to be distributed for Purim purposes, to the עניים.
aniyim. מגבי עיר לאותה עיר. Magbi ir le'osah ir. Some have a
question if that line belongs, but if it does, תוספות Tosafos says
what it means is when you collect from people in the city
on Purim, this is not a general rule, it has to be
spent for the עניים aniyim of that city.
ואין מדקדקים בדבר. Ve'ein medakdekim badavar. You do not say, oh my
God, we collected ten thousand dollars for מתנות לאביונים matanos la'evyonim for
Purim, you know, we'll spend a thousand dollars now, give them a
nice little meal and we'll put the rest, you know, for later.
No. It was all raised for Purim, you gotta spend it all,
even if it means you're buying them all steaks and whatever, you
know, and caviar, it doesn't matter. You gotta spend it for Purim.
ואין מדקדקים בדבר. Ve'ein medakdekim badavar. אבל לוקחים את העגלים ושוחטים ואוכלים
אותן. Aval lokchim es ha'agalim veshochtim ve'ochlim osan. You take calves and
you slaughter and you eat them, and you have huge feasts. והמותיר,
Ve-hamosir, if there is anything, but you don't try to economize. But
if there is anything left over, יפול לכיס של צדקה. yipol le-kis
shel tzedakah. Then you put it to צדקה. tzedakah. Now, that's in
terms of the responsibility of the city. What about the עניים? aniyim?
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rebbi Eliezer omer, מגבי פורים לפורים. Magbi Purim le-Purim.
The עני ani got the money for Purim, ואין העני רשאי ליקח
מהם רצועה לסנדלו. ve'ein ha'ani rashai likach mehem retzu'ah lesandalo.
He can't even use one dollar of it to buy a shoe
string. Okay, it all has to be spent for Purim purposes from
the עני's ani perspective. אלא אם כן התנה במעמד אנשי העיר, Ela
im ken hisnah be-ma'amad anshei ha'ir,
unless he stipulated that way with the people of the city that
he has a little, you know, discretion. דברי רבי יעקב, Divrei Rebbi
Yaakov, these are the words of רבי יעקב, Rebbi Yaakov, שאמר משום
רבי מאיר, she'amar mishum Rebbi Meir, and that's our רבי מאיר. Rebbi
Meir. So the point being, this isn't really about נקרא גזלן, nikra
gazlan, but this is more about רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir saying you
have to totally keep by the terms. You have no discretion. You
can't even use it to buy a shoe string. Now that doesn't
necessarily mean that נקרא גזלן. nikra gazlan. But anyways, that's at least
a רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל מיקל, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel meikal, and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
is lenient. Interesting that the ברייתא braisa frames it that way, it
doesn't tell you what he actually says. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says
no, דילמא התם נמי אדעתא דפורים הוא דיהב ליה אדעתא דמידי אחריני
לא יהב ליה. Dilma hasam nami ada'ata de-Purim hu deyhav lei ada'ata
demidi achrini lo yhav lei. That doesn't mean that any time you
change some terms. That means that it was a gift. Here's some
of my money and I'm giving it to you under this condition,
and I'm not giving it to you under another condition. That doesn't
mean, you know, that any time anybody stipulates things there's a sense
oh, you violated the terms, now all of a sudden you're liable.
Here it was a specific sense that I'm giving it to you
to use to buy food. Okay, so that maybe is more limited.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, אלא האי רבי מאיר, Ela hai
Rebbi Meir, the following רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. דתניא, Detanya, we taught
a ברייתא. braisa. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום רבי מאיר. Rebbi
Shimon ben Elazar omer mishum Rebbi Meir. הנותן דינר לעני ליקח לו
חלוק, Hanosan dinar le'ani likach lo chaluk,
I give a similar case, I give him a dollar to go
buy yourself a shirt. לא יקח בו טלית, Lo yikach bo tallis,
don't buy a טלית. tallis. טלית לא יקח בו חלוק. Tallis lo
yikach bo chaluk. מפני, Mipnei, and here's the key line, שמעביר על
דעתו של בעל הבית. shemavir al da'aso shel ba'al habayis. That certainly
seems like the רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir we had in mind because
that has the key phrase because you... going against the stipulations of
the owner. So you see somebody says something, you're bound by those
stipulations. Wait a minute! ודילמא שאני התם דאתו למחשדיה. Vedilma shani hasam
de'asu lenichshadi. No, no, no, that reason is if the עני ani
buys something else, people are going to suspect me. Why? דאמרי אינשי
De'amri inshi people say אמר פלניא זבנינא ליה לבושא לפלוני עניא. Amar
planya zavnina lei levusha liploni anya.
You though, you've been announcing that you're going to go ahead and
buy this עני ani a nice new suit, okay, ולא זבין ליה,
velo zavin lei, and yet we don't see him with a new
suit. אינמי—זבנינא ליה גלימא—you say you're going to buy him a nice
new coat, ולא זבין ליה, velo zavin lei, we don't see that
he had a coat. You don't, you don't keep your promises.
You bring some guy driving around in a car.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says no, that cannot be the reason.
If the reason is because of my reputation, אי הכי ליתני מפני
החשד. in hachi lisni mipnei hachshad. Then we would say the עני
ani can't spend it on anything else because of my—of suspicion. מהי
מפני שמעביר על דעתו של בעל הבית? Mai mipnei shemaavir al da'ato
shel ba'al habayis? It doesn't frame it that way. It says the
problem is it's because he's going against my rules, my stipulations. So
שמע מינה shma mina that shows that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
very much concerned about how you stipulate. שמע מינה משום דשינוי הוא
וכל המעביר על דעתו של בעל הבית נקרא גזלן. Shma mina mishum
deshinnui hu vechol hamaavir al da'ato shel ba'al habayis nikra gazlan. Now
the problem I have to though say is, and guys I'm sorry,
just one second, the problem—the problem is—is that we've proven that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir cares about not going against the בעל הבית ba'al
habayis stipulation. What we have not proven is the second half of
the statement, נקרא גזלן. nikra gazlan. Okay, I wasn't supposed to go
against it. The fact that that makes me like a גזלן, gazlan,
fully liable for anything, that has not been stipulated, but clearly רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir does care about that and that's one way of
reading the ברייתא. braisa. When you violate the rules, you're responsible.
When you, when you—